Guide to the Pearl Primus Collection, 1920-1994
American Dance Festival Archives
- Photographs, circa 1920-1992 and undated (Box OS3)
  - Prints, circa 1920-1992 and undated (Box OS3)
    - Publicity, circa 1940-1969 (Box 6)
      - Public Appearances by Primus, circa 1940-1969, 40 folders (Box 7)
        - Packing for Africa (Rosenwald Grant) (Rosalie Gwathmey), 1949 (Box 7)
        - Signing Autographs (Beckman), 1947 (Box 7)
        - Belgian Congo, 1949 (Box 7)
        - Primus with Family (Rosalie Gwathmey), 1949 (Box 7)
        - Women Dancers in Nigeria, 1949 (Box 7)
        - Jacob's Pillow, 1950 (Box 7)
        - Primus with Percival Borde, circa 1950-1959 (Box 7)
        - Primus with Francis Day, Jack Hylton reading program of Primus' royal performance, Oct. 29, 1951 (Box 7)
        - Appearance in U.K., (Keystone Press Agency), Oct. 1951 (Box 7)
        - Appearance In U.K (Daily Express), circa 1951 (Box 7)
        - Israeli tour (Hans Kaufmann), Jan. 1952 (Box 7)
        - Trieste, Italy, Oct.-Nov. 1956 (Box 7)
        - Primus with Percival Borde and Curtis J. Perkins (R. Walker), circa 1956 (Box 7)
        - Appearance with Onwin Borde, circa 1960 (Box 7)
        - Appearance, circa 1960-1969 (Box 7)
        - Appearance at Detroit Institute of the Arts, circa 1960-1969 (Box 7)
        - Primus with Percival Borde and Nun, circa 1960-1969 (Box 7)
        - Primus teaching children, circa 1960-1969 (Box OS2)
        - Primus with Nigerian Cultural Leaders, circa 1961 (Box 8)
        - Percival Borde presenting award, circa 1962 (Box 8)
        - Percival Borde with Miss Trinidad and Tobago Independence, Sept. 1962 (Box 8)
        - Press clipping: Everyman's African Roots, Dance Magazine, Oct. 1964 (Box 8)
        - Dancing Masks of Africa Exhibit Opening, Sept. 1974 (Box 8)
        - Spelman College Repertory Workshop, Swing Low (Reeves Studios), 1976 (Box 8)
        - Primus (Sigrid Estrada), circa 1982 (Box 8)
        - Contact Magazine shoot (Stephen Long), 1984 (Box 8)
        - Lecture Demonstration at Amherst (Frank Ward), circa 1986 (Box 8)
        - American Dance Festival Master Class (Jay Anderson), 1988 (Box 8)
        - Primus with Kim Bears, circa 1988 (Box 8)
        - Lecture Demonstration (Andre Richardson), circa 1980-1989 (Box 8)
        - National Medal of Arts (Vivian Ronay), 1991 (Box 8)
      - Photographs of Others, circa 1940-1969, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Photographs of others, identified, circa 1940-1969 (Box 8)
        - Photographs of others, unidentified, circa 1940-1969 (Box 8)
    - Performance, circa 1940-1969, 45 folders (Box 8)
      Includes photographs of Primus, her family, and her company taken by a professional photographer at live performances.
      - Performances, circa 1940-1979 (Box 8)
      - Prayer of Thanksgiving, Belgian Congo (A. Da Cruz), 1949 (Box 8)
      - Belgian Congo (A. Da Cruz), circa May-Aug. 1949 (Box 8)
      - Dance of Lightning, Belgian Congo (A. Da Cruz), circa May-Aug. 1949 (Box 8)
      - Jacob's Pillow, 1950 (Box 8)
      - Cleveland Performance (Bill Wingfield), circa 1950-1959 (Box 8)
      - International Festival, circa 1950-1959 (Box 8)
      - English Tour, 1951 (Box 8)
      - Primus Company, circa 1951 (Box 8)
      - Italian tour (Foto Florio), 1956 (Box 8)
      - Italian tour (E. Constantine), 1956 (Box 8)
      - Italian tour (L. de Rota), circa Oct.-Nov. 1956 (Box 8)
      - Primus with Percival Borde, NYU-TV (Irwin Gooen), 1957 (Box 8)
      - Percival Borde, circa 1960-1969 (Box 8)
      - Primus Company, circa 1960-1969 (Box 8)
      - NYU (William Simmons), 1962 (Box 8)
      - Appearance (Bro. David McAdams), June 25, 1964 (Box 8)
      - Alphonse Cimber, Primus Company drummer (E. Pen Stevens), Oct. 11, 1969 (Box 8)
      - Percival Borde, Primus Company, Lincoln Center Out-Of-Doors Festival (Dan Brinzac), Aug. 20, 1979 (Box 8)
      - Percival Borde, circa 1970-1979 (Box 8)
      - Percival Borde, Impinyuza, circa 1970-1979 (Box 8)
      - Primus with Onwin Borde, circa 1970-1979 (Box 8)
      - Performance, circa 1980-1989 (3 folders) (Box 8)
      - Unidentified Performers, circa 1980-1989 (Box 8)
      - Excerpts from an African Journey, Five College Faculty Dance Concert, 1984 (Box 8)
      - Mary François Brooks and Co., 1986 (Box 8)
      - Primus Company, undated (Box 8)
      - Primus Company (Costas), undated (Box 8)
      - Primus Company, Initiation, undated (Box 8)
      - Primus Company, Bushasche, undated (Box 8)
    - Snapshots, circa 1930-1992, 40 folders (Box 8)
      Includes photographs taken by non-professional, unidentified photographers. The images document Primus' family and friends, as well as some performances and appearances.
      - Emily and Edward Primus (parents), circa 1930-1939 (Box 9)
      - Others, circa 1930-1959 (Box 9)
      - Hunter College, Friends, circa 1937 (Box 9)
      - Primus, circa 1937-1950 (Box 9)
      - Primus with Family and Friends, circa 1937-1960 (Box 9)
      - Albums, including Father and Hunter College friend, 1938-1939 (Box 9)
      - Primus' Brothers and Sisters-in-Law, circa 1940-1949 (Box 9)
      - Others, signed, 1949 (Box 9)
      - Others, unidentified, 1949, 1959-1963 (Box 9)
      - Primus in Africa, circa 1949 (Box 9)
      - Watusi (Rwanda), circa 1949 (Box 9)
      - Primus at Café Society Downtown, 1950 (Box 9)
      - Yael Woll, circa 1950-1953 (Box 9)
      - Album, circa 1952 (Box 9)
      - Trinidad, circa 1953 (Box 9)
      - Trinidad albums, circa 1953 (5 folders) (Box 9)
      - Onwin Borde (with Primus and Percival Borde), 1955 (Box 9)
      - Africa, circa 1959-1963 (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Liberia, circa 1959-1963 (Box 9)
      - Onwin Borde, 1961 (Box 9)
      - Liberia, 1961 (Box 9)
      - Classes, circa 1965 (Box 9)
      - Percival Borde, Lagos, Nigeria, 1971 (Box 9)
      - Onwin Borde drumming, circa 1980-1989 (Box 9)
      - Lecture Demonstration, Emory University, Atlanta, circa 1980-1989 (Box 9)
      - Panel Discussion, circa 1980-1989 (Box 9)
      - Primus with Marilyn Middleton, circa 1980-1989 (Box 9)
      - Primus at White Plains High School, circa 1980-1989 (Box 9)
      - Shango de Ima, circa 1980-1989 (Box 9)
      - Unidentified, circa 1980-1994 (Box 9)
      - Primus at Murray and Peggy Schwartz's home, 1983 (Box 9)
      - Students, Dance Workshop, Apr. 6, 1984 (Box 9)
      - Primus with Maya Angelou and Onwin Borde, 1987 (Box 10)
      - Primus and Shepard Roderick, Barbados, circa 1987 (Box 10)
      - Primus at Murray and Peggy Schwartz's home, 1989 (Box 10)
      - Tokunaga Dance Kompany, Boston, circa 1992 (Box 10)
  - Contact Sheets, circa 1940-1984, 8 folders (Box 10)
    Arranged chronologically within three subseries: Publicity, Performance, and Snapshots.
    None of the contact sheets in this series has its accompanying negatives. There are, however, a few contact sheets with their accompanying negatives in the Negatives series.
    - Publicity, circa 1940-1959 (Box 10)
      - Primus and Company (or students), circa 1940-1949 (Box 10)
      - Primus Company Rehearsal, circa 1950-1959 (Box 10)
    - Performance, circa 1940-1984 (Box 10)
      - Primus, circa 1940-1949 (Box 10)
      - Primus at Jacob's Pillow, 1950 (Box 10)
      - Onwin Borde, circa 1965 (Box 10)
      - Primus with unidentified company, 1984 (Box 10)
    - Snapshots, circa 1950-1959 (Box 10)
      - Primus, circa 1950-1959 (Box 10)
      - Primus, Percival Borde, Onwin Borde, circa 1958 (Box 10)
  - Negatives, circa 1930-1988 and undated, 14 folders (Box 10)
    Arranged chronologically within the series of Portraits, Publicity, Performance, and Snapshots. Primus' negatives from her trips to Africa are arranged in a separate, following series.
    Contains some of the negatives of prints found in the Photographic Prints subseries. There are also numerous negatives of snapshots of family members with Onwin Borde, primarily during his infant and toddler years, 1955-1957. Other negatives include performances of Primus and other well-known modern dancers such as Jose Limon and Helen Tamiris at Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival in 1950.
    - Portraits, circa 1945 (Box 10)
      - Primus, circa 1945 (Box 10)
    - Publicity, circa 1945-1988 (Box 10)
      - Spirituals, circa 1945 (Box 10)
      - Primus, circa 1945-1988 (Box 10)
    - Performance, 1949-1950 (Box 10)
      - Dance of Lightning and Prayer of Thanksgiving, 1949 (Box 10)
      - Limon, Ide, Helen, Cimber, Lindquist, Rivera, Jacob's Pillow, 1950 (Box 10)
      - Dance of Lightning and The Negro Speaks of Rivers, 1950 (Box 10)
      - Primus, Jacob's Pillow, 1950 (Box 10)
    - Snapshots, circa 1930-1965 and undated (Box 10)
      - Unidentified, circa 1930-1949 (Box 10)
      - Primus and family, 1955-1957 (Box 10)
      - Children, including Onwin Borde, circa 1955-1959 (Box 10)
      - Percival Borde and Onwin Borde, circa 1960 (Box 10)
      - Onwin Borde, circa 1960 (Box 10)
      - Onwin Borde, circa 1965 (Box 10)
      - Primus and Percival Borde, undated (Box 10)
  - Primus' Ethnographic Studies from Africa, 1949, 1960-1963 (Box 10)
    This subseries consists of negatives and transpareancies taken by Primus in Africa in 1949 and 1960-1963. They document the people, landscapes, vegetation, habitats, crafts, instruments, dance, dress, and rituals of the African tribes she visited.
    - Negatives Identified by Primus, 1949, 1960-1963, 16 folders (Box 10)
      The negatives in this subseries were contained in an index card box and identified by Primus according to city or subject, although they were not arranged in their current alphabetical order.
      - Aba (Nigeria) (Box 10)
      - Benin (Nigeria) (Box 10)
      - Boma (Belgian Congo) (Box 10)
      - Bonny (Nigeria) (Box 10)
      - Duala (Cameroon) (Box 10)
      - Ife (Nigeria) (Box 10)
      - Jos (Nigeria) (Box 11)
      - Kalabar (Nigeria) (Box 11)
      - Kano (Nigeria) (Box 11)
      - Lagos (Nigeria) (Box 11)
      - Missions (Box 11)
      - Oron (Nigeria) (Box 11)
      - Ship (Box 11)
      - Usumbura (Burundi) (Box 11)
      - Warri (Nigeria) (Box 11)
      - Zaria (Nigeria) (Box 11)
    - Negatives not Identified by Primus, 1949, 13 folders (Box 11)
      The negatives in this subseries were tentatively identified or categorized by ADF Archives staff and arranged alphabetically by tribe or subject.
      The majority of these negatives likely date to Primus' 1949 Rosenwald Foundation grant tour.
      - Ashanti [?] (Ghana) (Box 11)
      - Bakuba (Belgian Congo) (4 folders) (Box 11)
      - Flora and Fauna (Box 11)
      - Ife [?] (Nigeria) (Box 11)
      - Kampo [?] (Senegal) (Box 11)
      - Mano (Liberia) (3 folders) (Box 11)
      - Material Culture (2 folders) (Box 11)
      - Primus (Box 11)
      - Watusi (Rwanda) (4 folders) (Box 11)
      - Unidentified Children (Box 11)
      - Unidentified People (4 folders) (Box 11)
    - Transparencies not Identified by Primus, 1949, 1960-1963, 2 folders (Box 11)
      The transparencies in this subseries were tentatively identified or categorized by ADF Archives staff and arranged alphabetically by tribe or subject.
      - Accra (Ghana), circa 1962 (Box 11)
      - Bakuba (Belgian Congo) (Box 11)
- Moving Images, circa 1949-1992, 22 items (Box 11)
  Viewing of these materials requires the use of reference copies. When a reference copy exists, it is noted in the finding aid. Originals are restricted.
  Arranged by format and then by item number, as assigned by the staff of Free to Dance.
  Includes 15 reels of 8mm film, primarily containing images of Africa shot by Primus in either 1949 or 1960 to 1963. This series also contains amateur VHS footage of Alvin Ailey American Dance Theatre rehearsing Primus' Impinyuza and of a speech Primus presented at Howard University in 1992. Also present is an interview with Primus conducted for the Standifer Oral History Archive in 1989, as well as a 1981 feature on Primus by Schenectady PBS affiliate WMHT. Titles are transcribed from the original label on each item.
  - 8 mm Film, circa 1949-1969 (Box 11)
    Films marked with an asterisk* are also represented on Reference Copy DVD #4781 (Box 16), Preservation Copy Betacam SP #4781 (Box 13), and Preservation Copy DigiBeta #4781 (Box 13). Originals and preservation copies are restricted.
    - 051-01-5 50' B/W Bullfight* (Box 12)
    - 051-03-5 dancing outside, in front of two doors-very light (Box 12)
    - 051-04-5 Great Wall, Donkeys, Looks like more African dancing, 1960s* (Box 12)
    - 051-05-5 Native Guitar, Street in Lagos (Box 12)
    - 051-06-5 Pearl at Jacob's Pillow (Box 12)
    - 051-07-5 Bullfight, color* (Box 12)
    - 051-08-5 50' B/W, good exposure. Probably not Africa-people coming out of buildings (Box 12)
    - 051-09-5 50' color Bullfight* (Box 12)
    - 051-10-5 looks like female African standing, then dancing in road. Full roll (Box 12)
    - 051-11-5 dancing, color. Soloist in white skirt* (Box 12)
    - 051-14-5 sheep or cow under a tree* (Box 12)
    - 051-15-5 color-very light* (Box 12)
    - 051-16-5 the road, shot from inside a car, color* (Box 12)
    - 051-17-5 date: 1958 house/hut/tent color* (Box 12)
    - 051-18-5 person standing in front of stairs* (Box 12)
  - VHS Videocassettes, circa 1989-1992 and undated (Box 12)
    Videocassettes marked with an asterisk* are represented on individual reference copy DVDs (Box 16) and individual preservation copy Betacam SP videocassettes (Box 13). Originals and preservation copies are restricted.
    - 051-12-4 Pearl Primus in Africa* (Box 13)
    - 051-13-4 Sathi Ailey Impinyuza-Sun. 10/21 TRT: 23:22 5/21/92* (Box 13)
    - 051-14-4 Luncheon at Howard University 1992* (Box 13)
    - 051-15-4 Impinyuza Rehearsal 8/7/90 (Box 13)
    - 051-16-4 Dr. Pearl Primus Interviewed by James Standifer, Feb. 16, 1989 (Box 13)
  - U-Matic Videocassettes, 1981 (Box 13)
    These two tapes are represented on a single reference copy DVD (Box 16) and two individual preservation copy Betacam SP videocassettes (Box 13). Originals and preservation copies are restricted.
    - Pearl Primus, Mon. 4/20/81, WMHT-NY (2 videocassettes) (Box 13)
- Sound Recordings, 1950-1989 and undated, 68 items (Box 13)
  Listening to these materials requires the use of reference copies. Sound recordings marked with an asterisk* are also represented on individual reference copy audio CDs (Box 16). Originals are restricted.
  Arranged by format and by identifying numbers assigned by ADF staff.
  Contains 1/4-inch reel-to-reel audiotapes and audiocassettes belonging to Primus, including interviews with Primus in 1950 and 1956 and a lecture-demonstration on Dance and Life Crisis. This series also contains a copy of Pearl Primus' Africa, a set of three phonograph records of African stories, proverbs, and songs that Primus narrated, as well as copies of four other native music LPs. Also included are recordings of chants, drumming, and singing likely used to accompany rehearsals, or perhaps made to preserve native songs and rhythms for future study, although these are largely unidentified. Home recordings and duplicates of popular music, including Josh White, Miles Davis, Langston Hughes, and Billie Holiday, are also included.
  Titles are copied from the original labels on the boxes of the sound reels and audiocassettes. Additional notes appear in brackets, including spelled-out abbreviations and uncertain readings of illegible titles.
  - 1/4-Inch Reel-to-Reel Audiotapes, 1950-1988 and undated (Box 13)
    - PPCAud1 Fanti + Group/Fanga* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud2 Shango Songs* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud3 Priorities* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud4 Hard Times Blues 6/88 (Box 14)
    - PPCAud5 Fanga* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud6 P. Primus Lecture Coldstream* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud7 George Carvell, Hoffman Elementary School, Hoffman and Church St., Elmira, NY 14905 (Box 14)
    - PPCAud8 Unidentified (Box 14)
    - PPCAud9 Unidentified (Box 14)
    - PPCAud10 Unidentified (Box 14)
    - PPCAud11 Aug-Sept 1955, Music and Talk-Pearl, Percy, Hada[mar?] Nul[tor?], 1st part Carr[icecon] [Sonny, Arnette]-Sept. 22/55, Belle pique, Cacoa oh Cacoa, Rock Daniel, Rattle* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud11 Aug-Sept 1955, Music and Talk-Pearl, Percy, Hada[mar?] Nul[tor?], 1st part Carr[icecon] [Sonny, Arnette]-Sept. 22/55, Belle pique, Cacoa oh Cacoa, Rock Daniel, Rattle* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud12 Newark 7/9/57* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud13 Round Table Discussion, African Theater Arts, P.P. and P.B. [Pearl Primus and Percival Borde], [Ezra Koli?], P. Reynolds, W. Edwards, L. Jones, 11/2/73* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud14 St. Marks 1/hour 5 weeks 9/23 to 10/26, Bondi + Company, Primus Guest Artist* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud15 Records of [James and ?] with K. [Heldek?] Shango* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud16 Unidentified* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud17 Nights in Latin America-Rumba (Box 14)
    - PPCAud18 Unidentified* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud19 Jack Lathrop 1951, Pearl Primus, Conn. Coll., Aug. 1950* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud20 Radio Interview P. Primus, Callinda Drumming, Sam and [Tiny?], Pearl Primus, 17 W. 24th Studio, Sun. April 8, 1956* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud21 Recording of Drums and Singing By K. Ablack* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud22 Unlabeled* (Box 14)
      Letter from Koko to Primus identifies reel as recordings by Koko given to Primus. Original letter is in Correspondence, undated
    - PPCAud23 May 56 Speed Slow, Blue Sands-Buddy Collet [Collette], June 12 56, 'Dance off Buddy Fantaloon Dance Off' Onwin Primus, 'Big Foot Mary' Drumming by Onwin, Onwin on drums 1 yr later July 1 '57 age 2 1/2* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud24 Unidentified* (Box 14)
  - Audiocassettes, 1973-1989 and undated (Box 14)
    - PPCAud25 Sides 1 and 2: 321X Class 3/13/73* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud26 Sides 1 and 2: Lecture* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud27 Side 1: For transcript, Dance Studies; Side 2: African Dance Studies for transcription 7/9/75, Fanga* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud28 Side 1: Explaining Talking Drum by Timi of [Cede] 8/5/73; Side 2: Blank* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud29 Side 1: The Gay Flamingoes, Secrets of the Pan, 4 Selections; Side 2: Unidentified* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud30 Sides 1 and 2: Spring 74 Lect[ure] at Sus Valley School* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud31 Side 1: Praise Song 8/17/73 Osun; Side 2: Blank* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud32 Side 1: Notes on Artifacts, BOCES Stamford NY; Side 2: Blank* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud33 Sides 1 and 2: Others [Side 2 only on reference CD]* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud34 Sides 1 and 2: Summer Institute in Ethnic Studies Through the Arts* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud35 Sides 1 and 2: Festac 77 [2nd World Black and African Festival of Art and Culture, Jan. 1977]* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud36 Side 1: Arabo's Younger Brother 8/10/75; Side 2: Lagos 1st Bata Narrative* (Box 14)
    - PPCAud37 Side 1: 1-216 WA 107 Caribbean-137 (Box 14)
    - PPCAud38 Side 1: Discipline Bai T. Moon 8/12, Cultural Center 'in the Bush' 8/13; Side 2: Cultural Center 8/13 Lect[ure] Demo[nstration] (Box 14)
    - PPCAud39 Sides 1 and 2: Hi Life and JuJu Music (Box 14)
    - PPCAud40 Side 1: 8/9 5[?]-1st Part, Egon Gun-2nd part; Side 2: Egon Gun Lagos, Low Battery-8/9/75 (Box 14)
    - PPCAud41 Side 1: Italian-B and B Fall 1973 project; Side 2: Blank (Box 14)
    - PPCAud42 Side 1: Wisconsin #1-Superior; Side 2: Superior Wisc 1971 (Box 14)
    - PPCAud43 Side 1: Why Mosquitoes Buzz (Box 14)
    - PPCAud44 Side 1: Lect[ure] 292, 1st pt of Report, W.A., 71; Side 2: Report 1971 (cont) (Box 14)
    - PPCAud45 Side 1: African Rhythms; Side 2: Lecture Caribbean Music-4/18/79 M101 Blank (Box 14)
    - PPCAud46 Side 1: Paraverbal Meeting 11/3/89 (Box 14)
    - PPCAud47 Side 1: 292B Black Theatre; Side 2: 292B Africa Theatre (Box 14)
    - PPCAud48 Side 1: Drama/Dance Nigeria Dundun Set; Side 2: Yoruba Class 8/1/73 (Box 14)
    - PPCAud49 Side 1: 5/8/74 [A Allvelty?]; Side 2: French Class (Box 14)
    - PPCAud50 Side 1: Borroff (Box 14)
    - PPCAud51 Unidentified (Box 14)
    - PPCAud52 Unidentified (Box 14)
    - PPCAud53 Side 1: Lect at Chicago [?] Forks-10/16/75; Side 2: Cheuougo Forks Lect 10/21/75 (Box 14)
    - PPCAud54 Side 1: Seminar on Report 11/22 (Box 14)
    - PPCAud55 Side 1: African Article Report 11/17; Side 2: Asleiti Conference 11/17 (Box 14)
    - PPCAud56 Side 1: PSU Lect Oregon 6/21; Side 2: Lect-P.S.U. (Box 14)
    - PPCAud57 Sides 1 and 2: Radical Liberal Arts May 1988 (Box 14)
    - PPCAud58 Side 1: AA/Thea 137 and 207 c/w 5/8/74 (Box 14)
    - PPCAud59 Side 1: Tue Dije 8/9/73; Side 2: Tue Dije 8/9/73 (Box 14)
    - PPCAud60 Sides 1 and 2: Ron Christopher st (Box 14)
    - PPCAud61 Side 1: Nigerian Music Examples Spirit Movement (background music for slides and skit) (Box 14)
    - PPCAud62 Sides 1 and 2: Langston Hughes/Miles Davis/Billie Holiday (Box 14)
    - PPCAud63 Sides 1 and 2: Billie Holiday (Box 14)
  - Long-Playing Records (Box 14)
    - PPCAud64 Pearl Primus' Africa* (Box 15)
    - PPCAud65 The Talking Drums* (Box 15)
    - PPCAud66 Drums of Haiti* (Box 15)
    - PPCAud67 Negro Folk Music of Africa and America* (Box 15)
    - PPCAud68 African Dances and Games* (Box 15)
- Artifacts, 1974-1991 and undated, 2.92 linear feet (Box 15)
  Costumes (Box 18) are restricted.
  Contains seven plaques, awarded for achievement in modern dance, anthropology, and teaching, and the 1991 Medal of Arts, awarded by President George H. W. Bush. This series also contains three female and one male ballet slippers, assumed to have belonged to Primus and her husband, Percival, and three dance costumes presumably worn by Primus. Notable is the one identifiable costume, worn by Primus during performances of The Negro Speaks of Rivers and Strange Fruit in the mid-1940s.
  - Appreciation presented by African Heritage Class and African-American Heritage Dance Club, 1974 (Box 17)
  - Outstanding Pioneer Award presented by Audelco, 1977 (Box 17)
  - Ernest Melby Award presented by NYU Alumni Association, 1986 (Box 17)
  - Honorary Citizen of Atlanta, 1989 (Box 17)
  - Distinguished Achievement Award presented by Association of Black Anthropologists, 1991 (Box 17)
  - National Medal of Arts, 1991 (Box 17)
  - Olaudah Equiano Award of Excellence, University of Utah, 1994 (Box 17)
  - Ballet shoes (three women's and one men's) (Box 17)
  - Brown woven circle (Box 17)
  - P. Borde name Tag (Box 17)
  - Rosary (Box 17)
  - Woodblock stamp of image from African Ceremonial (Box 17)
  - Wooden comb (Box 17)
  - Restricted: Black striped skirt with pink trim, from Negro Speaks of Rivers and Strange Fruit (Box 18)
  - Restricted: Blue and purple velvet dress with leaves (Box 18)
  - Restricted: Purple dress (Box 18)